A Guide to the Curley Collins Collection, 1928-2009
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Curley Collins Collection, 1928-2009
The Library of Virginia
40983
0.45 cubic feet, 9 compact discs, and 1 cassette (2 boxes)
Collins, Ruey
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Phillip G. Collins, 10 December 2003.
Additional gift of Phillip G. Collins, June 2009.
Biographical Information
Ruey "Curley" Collins was born in Catlettsburg, Kentucky, on 28 July 1915. At an early age, his father, Neal Collins, taught him to play the banjo. He joined the family band at twelve years old. In addition to the banjo, Curley Collins played the guitar, mandolin, fiddle, and harmonica. The fiddle became his primary instrument after winning the National Fiddle Championship in Atlanta in 1938.
Around 1929, he began playing with his first road band, the Mountain Melody Boys. Throughout his career, Curley Collins performed on numerous radio stations, including WSAZ in Huntington, West Virginia, WSB in Atlanta, WWVA in Wheeling, West Virginia, WRVA in Richmond. He also entertained on a number of country music shows, such as the Cross Roads Follies, Pop Eckler's Radio Jamboree, WWVA Jamboree, Old Dominion Barn Dance, and Virginia's Lil' Ole Opry.
Curley Collins was made a Kentucky Colonel in 1983, and inducted into the Atlanta Country Music Hall Fame in 1984 and the Old Dominion Barn Dance Hall of Fame in 1991.
He died in Richmond on 27 October 1986.
Scope and Content
The Curley Collins Collection, 1928-2009, includes advertisements, articles, certificates of award, clippings, magazines, photographs, and sound recordings documenting the life and musical career of Ruey "Curley" Collins (1915-1986), an award-winning fiddler and country musician. Includes material on the time he spent playing with the following bands: Mountain Melody Boys, Prairie Pals, Pop Eckler and His Young'uns, and Tennessee Ramblers; on the following radio and television program: WWVA Jamboree in Wheeling, West Virginia, the Old Dominion Barn Dance in Richmond, Virginia, and Country Music Time in Richmond, Virginia; and with the following shows: Richmond Country Style in Richmond, Virginia; and Virginia's Lil' Ole Opry in Mathews, Virginia.
Also includes information on Neal "Pop" Collins, Curley's father, and Curley's marriage to Kaki Williams on a program of the Old Dominion Barn Dance at the Richmond Mosque (now the Landmark Theater) on 19 March 1949.
The sound recordings include nine compact discs and one cassette of Benny Kissinger and Curley at Virginia's Lil' Ole Opry at Donk's Theater in Mathew County, Virginia from July 1980 to June 1985, "Benny and Curley Sing-Nashville Picks" in 1981, and the reunion of the Old Dominion Barn Dance on March 23, 1975. The audio on the compact discs was extracted in October 2005 and saved onto the server.
This collection was compiled by his son, Phillip G. Collins.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Historical Information, 1928-2009
II. Sound Recordings, 1975-1985
Contents List
- Historical Information, 1928-2009, 0.45 cu. ft. (1 box). (Box 1)
  Arranged according to the Table of Contents in Folder 1 with miscellaneous material arranged to the rear in alphabetical order.
  - Table of Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Genesis - Neal (Pop) Collins, 1930-1978. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mountain Melody Boys, 1928-1986. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Prairie Pals, 1935-1938. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Pop Eckler and His Youn'uns, 1936-1980. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - WWVA Jamboree, 1946-1977. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Tennessee Ramblers, 1946. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Old Dominion Barn Dance, 1946-1975. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Old Dominion Barn Dance - Wedding of Curley Collins and Kaki Williams, 1949. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Country Music Time, 1964. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Richmond Country Style, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Virginia's Lil' Ole Opry, 1978-1985. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, Awards and Certificates, 1983-2006. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous, Biographical Information (I-II), 1981-2002. (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Miscellaneous, Clippings, 1941-2009. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous, Country Music Columns (Norman Rowe), 1981-1992. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous, Country Music History, 1984. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, Photographs, 1944-1983. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Benny and Curley: Stars of the Old Dominion Barn Dance, International Country Music Journal, 2013. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    This article was added to the collection by an LVA staff member in 2013.
- Sound Recordings, 1975-1985, 9 audio compact discs and 1 cassette (1 box) (Box 2)
  Includes recordings of Benny Kissinger and Curley at Virginia's Lil' Ole Opry at Donk's Theater in Mathew County, Virginia from July 1980 to June 1985, and singing "Nashville Picks" in 1981. Also includes a recording of the reunion of the Old Dominion Barn Dance on March 23, 1975. Collection includes both a compact disc and a cassette for "Benny and Curley Sing Nashville Picks."
  The audio on the compact discs was extracted in October 2005 and saved onto the server.
  - Live from the "Lil Ol Opry" - Benny and Curley, July 1980 - February 1983, Disc 1; Audio compact disc. (Box 2)
  - Live from the "Lil Ol Opry" - Benny and Curley, March 1983, Disc 2; Audio compact disc. (Box 2)
  - Live from the "Lil Ol Opry" - Benny and Curley, October 15, 1983, Disc 3-4; Audio compact disc. (Box 2)
  - Live from the "Lil Ol Opry" - Benny and Curley, [n.d.], Disc 5; Audio compact disc. (Box 2)
  - Live from the "Lil Ol Opry" - Benny and Curley, March 1984 - June 1984, Disc 6; Audio compact disc. (Box 2)
  - Live from the "Lil Ol Opry" - Benny and Curley, August 1984 - June 1985, Disc 7; Audio compact disc. (Box 2)
  - The Old Dominion Barn Dance Presents Old Timers Day Featuring Sunshine Sue, March 23, 1975, Disc 8; Audio compact disc. (Box 2)
  - Benny and Curley Sing-Nashville Picks, 1981, Disc 9; Audio compact disc. (Box 2)
  - Benny and Curley Sing-Nashville Picks, 1981, Audio cassette. (Box 2)